Charles Mason Remey Papers
Charles Mason Remey Papers
1912-1958
Remey, Charles Mason, 1874-1974.
19 linear ft.
American architect. Collection includes manuscripts and published material.
2746184
Biographical History
Charles Mason Remey (1874-1974) was an American architect and author and adherent of the Baha'i faith. He designed and built Baha'i houses of worship in Uganda and Ethiopia (three others were designed but never constructed), and traveled extensively to promote the religion. In 1960, following the death of Shoghi Effendi without having appointed a successor, Remey proclaimed himself Guardian, or worldwide head, of the Baha'i. This claim caused significant consternation within the church, but was swiftly rejected by the vast majority of Baha'i worldwide and Remey was formally excommunicated (declared a Covenant-breaker) that same year. Remey relocated to Italy and, although retaining some adherents in the United States, Pakistan, and India, his influence gradually waned until his death in 1974.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Charles Mason Remey Papers includes published and self-published writings.
Published material is almost entirely related to the Baha'i faith: its history, practice, teaching, and architecture. Of particular interest are proposals for an indexing system for Baha'i writings, and a guide on the preservation and arrangement of Baha'i manuscript. The only item unrelated to Baha'i is an account of four-month cruise in the Bahamas.
Self-published material is almost all connected with the history of the Remey family. The bound volumes are typescript carbons with photographs, maps, and other material tipped in. Based on information stamped on the covers, several sets of these volumes were produced. The contents include letters, reminiscences, diaries, travel journals, designs for mausoleums, and more. In addition to Remey himself, other family members represented include his mother, Mary Josephine Mason Remey; his father, Rear Admiral George Collier Remey; and his grandfather Charles Mason, Chief Justice of Iowa.
Arrangement of the Collection
The collection is subdivided into published and unpublished material; within each series, volumes are arranged alphabetically by title.
Subject and Genre Headings
Architects; Biography; Religion and philosophy; Mason, Charles, 1804-1882.; Remey, Charles Mason, 1874-1974.; Remey, Mary Josephine Mason, 1845-1938.; Remey family.; Remey (Ship: DD-688); United States. -- Navy -- Officers.; Admirals -- United States.; Architects -- United States.; Architecture -- United States.; Bahai Faith -- History.; Bahai Faith -- Study and teaching.; Bahai temples.; Judges -- Iowa.; Europe -- Description and travel.; Latin America -- Description and travel.; Diaries.; Manuscripts (document genre); Memoirs.; Photographs.
Access Restrictions
There are no access restrictions on this material.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Charles Mason Remey, 1961.
Inventory
- Published writings
  - Baha'i Manuscripts - Suggestions for Their Preservation and Arrangement, 1923 (Box 1)
  - The Baha'i Movement for Universal Religion, Brotherhood and Peace - A Sketch of its History and Teaching (Washington D.C., Persian American Bulletin), 1912 (Box 1)
  - Baha'i Teaching - Quotations from the Bahai Sacred Writings and Several Articles upon the History and Aims of the Teaching (Washington D.C.), 1917 (Box 1)
  - Constructive Principles of the Bahai Movement - A Summary of the History, Object and Institutions of the Bahai Religious Teachings (Chicago, Bahai Publishing Society), 1917 (Box 1)
  - The Covenant ("published in the year XXI of the Miniistry of Abdul-Baha"), [1919?] (Box 1)
  - Mashrak-El-Azkar - Descriptive of the Bahai temple and illustrative of an exhibition of preliminary designs for the first Mashrak-El-Azkar to be built in America, showing nine varying treatments in different styles of architecture (Bahai Publishing Society, Chicago), 1917 (Box 1)
  - The National Church and Shrine - Its Design, Organization and Work (Washington, D.C., Organizers of the National Church Foundation), 1929 (Box 1)
  - The National Church and Shrine of the United States of America to be Built in the City of Washington (Washington, D.C., Organizers of the National Church), 1927 (Box 1)
  - Das Neue Zeitalter - die Bahai-Offenbarung von Charles Mason Remey [translated into German by Wilhelm Herrigel] (Stuttgart, Verlag des Deutschen Bahaibundes Stuttgart), 1923 (Box 1)
  - Observations of a Bahai Traveler, Second Edition ([Washington, D.C.?], Bahai Publishing Society), 1914 (Box 1)
  - A Series of Twelve Articles Introductory to the Study of the Baha'i Teachings (Baha'i Publishing Committee, [New York?]), 1925 (Box 1)
  - Suggestions for the Arrangement of a Bibliography and Reference Indexes of the Baha'i Teachings with Practical Explanations of How to Build Up Baha'i Index Systems, 1923 (Box 2)
  - The Universal Consciousness of the Baha'i Religion (Baha'i Publishing Committee, [New York?]), 1925 (Box 2)
  - We Called it a Vacation [alternatively titled by CMR on cover: "Account of a Yachting Cruise of Four Months in the Bahamas"] by George Remey Wadleigh (New York, John Felsberg Inc.), 1950 (Box 2)
- Self-published writings
  - Architectural Design for the Baha'i Temple to be Built Upon Mount Carmel in the Holy Land, 1948 (Box 2)
  - The Biography of a House - a Monograph in Two Parts, 2 volumes (Box 2)
  - The Daily Diary of Charles Mason Remey, 1940 (Box 2)
  - The Daily Diary of Charles Mason Remey, 1941 (Box 2)
  - The Daily Diary of Charles Mason Remey, 1942; 2 volumes (Box 2)
  - The Daily Diary of Charles Mason Remey, 1943; 2 volumes (Box 3)
  - The Daily Diary of Charles Mason Remey, 1944 (Box 3)
  - The Daily Diary of Charles Mason Remey, 1945; 2 volumes (Box 3)
  - The Daily Diary of Charles Mason Remey, 1946 (Box 3)
  - The Daily Diary of Charles Mason Remey, 1947 (Box 3)
  - The Daily Diary of Charles Mason Remey, 1947-1948 (Box 3)
  - The Daily Diary of Charles Mason Remey, 1948; 2 copies (Box 3)
  - Five Preliminary Architectural Sketches for the Temple of the Mashrak-El-Azkar Which the Followers of the Bahai Movement are to Build Upon the Shore of Lake Michigan at Chicago (Box 4)
  - Herbert's Diary - an Account of Trailer Travels [ed. by Remey] (Box 4)
  - Houses in Which the Remey Family and the For-Bears[sic] have Lived, 2 volumes (Box 4)
  - Illustrated Description of a Design in the Persian-Indian Style of Architecture for the First Mashrak-El-Azkar (Bahai Temple) to be Erected in America, Humbly Offered to the Center of the Covenant Through the Bahai Temple Unity, April 26-28, 1920 (Box 4)
  - In Memoriam Ezekiel Gilbert Gear 1793-1873, sketch of the minister of the Episcopal Church in America (Box 4)
  - Journal Diary European Baha'i Travels, 1948; 3 volumes (Box 4)
  - Journal Diary of Baha'i Travels in Europe, part 1, 1947 (Box 4)
  - Journal Diary of Baha'i Travels in Europe, part 2, 1947 (Box 5)
  - Journal Diary of Baha'i Travels in Latin America, 1946-1947; 2 volumes (Box 5)
  - Letters Treating of Baha'i Activities (Box 5)
  - Life and Letters of Charles Mason, Chief Justice of Iowa, 1804-1882 v. 1-2 ("Edited and arranged by his eldest grandson Charles Mason Remey"), 1939; 2 folders (Box 5)
  - Life and Letters of Charles Mason, Chief Justice of Iowa, 1804-1882 v. 3-6 ("Edited and arranged by his eldest grandson Charles Mason Remey"), 1939; 4 folders (Box 6)
  - Life and Letters of Charles Mason, Chief Justice of Iowa, 1804-1882, v. 7-10 ("Edited and arranged by his eldest grandson Charles Mason Remey"), 1939; 4 folders (Box 7)
  - Life and Letters of Charles Mason, Chief Justice of Iowa, 1804-1882, v. 11-12 ("Edited and arranged by his eldest grandson Charles Mason Remey"), 1939; 2 folders (Box 8)
  - Life and Letters of Mary Josephine Mason Remey, Wife of Rear Admiral George Collier Remey, Daughter of Chief Justice Charles Mason, 1845-1938 v. 1-3 ("Edited and arranged by her eldest son Charles Mason Remey"), 1939; 3 folders (Box 8)
  - Life and Letters of Mary Josephine Mason Remey, Wife of Rear Admiral George Collier Remey, Daughter of Chief Justice Charles Mason, 1845-1938 v. 4-8 ("Edited and arranged by her eldest son Charles Mason Remey"), 1939; 5 folders (Box 9)
  - Life and Letters of Mary Josephine Mason Remey, Wife of Rear Admiral George Collier Remey, Daughter of Chief Justice Charles Mason, 1845-1938 v. 9-12 ("Edited and arranged by her eldest son Charles Mason Remey"), 1939; 4 folders (Box 10)
  - Life and Letters of Rear Admiral George Collier Remey, United States Navy, 1841-1928 v. 1 ("Edited and arranged by his eldest son Charles Mason Remey"), 1939 (Box 10)
  - Life and Letters of Rear Admiral George Collier Remey, United States Navy, 1841-1928 v. 2-6 ("Edited and arranged by his eldest son Charles Mason Remey"), 1939; 5 folders (Box 11)
  - Life and Letters of Rear Admiral George Collier Remey, United States Navy, 1841-1928 v. 7-10 ("Edited and arranged by his eldest son Charles Mason Remey"), 1939; 4 folders (Box 12)
  - The Mausoleum of the Remey Family, 1945 (Box 12)
  - The National Church, 1926 (Box 12)
  - The National Church and Shrine, 1926 (Box 13)
  - Preliminary Designs for the Remey Family Mausoleum, 1954 (Box 13)
  - A Record of the USS Remey (Box 13)
  - The Remevm - Place of Commemoration and Sepvltvre of the Family of Rear Admiral George Collier Remey Vnited States Navy and his wife Mary Josephine Mason Their Descendants, For-Bears and Friends, 1958 (Box 13)
  - The Remey Family 1654-1954, 1957 (Box 13)
  - Reminiscences and Letters v. 1-2, 2 volumes (Box 13)
  - Reminiscences and Letters v. 3-7, 5 volumes (Box 14)
  - Reminiscences and Letters v. 8-11, 4 volumes (Box 15)
  - Reminiscences and Letters v. 12-16, 5 volumes (Box 16)
  - Reminiscences and Letters v. 17-21, 5 volumes (Box 17)
  - Reminiscences and Letters v. 22-26, 5 volumes (Box 18)
  - Reminiscences and Letters v. 27-32, 6 volumes (Box 19)
  - Reminiscences and Letters v. 33-37, 5 volumes (Box 20)
  - Reminiscences and Letters v. 38-42, 5 volumes (Box 21)
  - Reminiscences and Letters v. 43-47, 5 volumes (Box 22)
  - Reminiscences and Letters v. 48-52, 5 volumes (Box 23)
  - Reminiscences and Letters v. 53-57, 5 volumes (Box 24)
  - Reminiscences and Letters v. 58-62, 5 volumes (Box 25)
  - Reminiscences and Letters v. 63-68, 6 volumes (Box 26)
  - Reminiscences and Letters v. 69-74, 6 volumes (Box 27)
  - Reminiscences and Letters v. 75-80, 6 volumes (Box 28)
  - Reminiscences and Letters v. 81-85, 5 volumes (Box 29)
  - Reminiscences and Letters v. 86-91, 6 volumes (Box 30)
  - Reminiscences and Letters v. 92-97, 6 volumes (Box 31)
  - Reminiscences and Letters v. 98-102, 5 volumes (Box 32)
  - Reminiscences and Letters v. 103-107, 5 volumes (Box 33)
  - Reminiscences and Letters v. 108-111 (4 folders), 4 volumes (Box 34)
  - Reminiscences and Letters v. 112-116, 4 volumes (Box 35)
  - Reminiscences and Letters v. 117-119, 3 volumes (Box 36)
  - Reminiscences of Green Acre, 1949; 2 volumes (Box 36)
  - Reminiscences of His Boyhood v. 1 (Box 37)
  - Reminiscences of His Childhood v. 1-4, 4 volumes (Box 37)
  - Reminiscent of Colonel William Butler Remey United States Marine Corps and Lieutenant Edward Wallace Remey United States Navy, 1955 (Box 37)
  - A Teacher of the Baha'i Faith in South America parts 1 and 2, 1945-1946; 2 folders (Box 37)
  - A Teacher of the Baha'i Faith in South America part 3, 1945-1946 (Box 38)
  - Through Warring Countries to the Mountain of God, 1915 (Box 38)